Guide to the New York City Central Labor Council Oral History Collection OH.007
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
New York City Central Labor Council Oral History Collection
1987, 1999-2006
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
AFL-CIO. New York City Central Labor Council
OH.007
13.63 Linear Feet in 1 half-manuscript box, 2 cassette boxes, and 1 CD box
53 audiocassettes
1 VHS
51 CD-ROM
319 kilobytes in 2 documents
The New York City Central Labor Council Oral History Collection consists of interviews and meetings with labor union leaders, recorded on audiocassette. The interviews contain oral histories of union organizers, some of who were active at the time the organization was charted by the American Federation of Labor (AFL) in the 1920s. Other recordings document NYC-CLC meetings held between 1999-2006.
Conditions Governing Access
Materails are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by New York City Central Labor Council in several installments in circa 1986. The accession number associated with this gift is 1986.037.
Arrangement
The recordings from 1987 are organized by the last name of the interviewee; recordings made between 1999-2006 are organized by date.
Transcripts for multi-part interviews with born-digital materials are listed only under part one of the interview.
Biographical / Historical
The New York City Central Labor Council had its origins in the Central Trades and Labor Council of Greater New York City, chartered in 1920 by the American Federation of Labor (AFL). The Council represented AFL-affiliated local unions in the New York City area. After the split between the AFL and the newly-formed Congress of Industrial Organizations (CIO) in the mid-1930s, CIO unions in the city were represented by a separate CIO Council. The Central Trades and Labor Council merged with the New York City CIO on February 19, 1959 to form the New York City Central Labor Council, AFL-CIO. This move followed the 1955 national merger of the AFL and the CIO, and the 1958 merger of New York state-level AFL and CIO bodies.
The New York City Central Labor Council is an organization comprised of nearly 400 local union affiliates. It only acts on local activities and concerns. It issues no statements on AFL-CIO policy and does not participate in the affairs of its local affiliates or their parent organizations. Its purpose, according to its constitution, is to further the rights of workers to organize in unions and bargain collectively; to advocate legislation which is beneficial to workers and oppose that which is not; to correct abuses and to insure the workers their just rights. It also has the broader purposes of helping all workers to improve their working conditions and raise their standard of living; to preserve workers' rights to act together for mutual aid and advancement; to further the cause of trade unions; and to strengthen civil rights. It acts as the central body of the City's labor movement, providing assistance and education through its various committees and councils.
The regular activities of the New York City Central Labor Council are directed by its executive officers, Executive Board, and Delegates' Council meetings. The planning and execution of programs and conferences is the province of a number of standing and special committees. These committees are composed of members from affiliated local unions, and each has its own officers and advisory staff. And is responsible for conducting specific programs and conferences. An important special committee is the Labor Day Parade Committee.
Harry Van Arsdale, Business Manager of International Brotherhood of Electricians Local 3, was elected the president of the Central Trades and Labor Council of the AFL in 1957. With the merger in 1959 he became the president of the Central Labor Council. During his presidency (1957-1986), the council established many committees and programs such as the Rehabilitation Council (1963), Hispanic Labor Committee (1970), and the Black Trade Unionists Leadership Committee (1972). After Harry Van Arsdale Jr.'s death in 1986, his son, Thomas Van Arsdale was elected to the post of president. During the Van Arsdales' tenure the Council campaigned to organize taxicab drivers, helped to found a worker education program (the Harry Van Arsdale, Jr. Center for Labor Studies at Empire State College, SUNY), mobilized the labor movement to confront the City's fiscal crisis of the late 1970s, and generally worked to foster a spirit of solidarity throughout the many disparate sectors of the New York City labor movement
Thomas Van Arsdale was succeeded as president by Brian M. McLaughlin, also of IBEW Local 3, in 1995; and Gary LaBarbera of the Teamsters union was elected to replace McLaughlin in June 2007, with Ed Ott serving in the newly created position of Executive Director.
The Council's web site is http://www.nycclc.org/
Related Materials
New York City Central Labor Council Records (WAG 049)
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of 50 audiocassettes organized into two parts. One part is a collection of recorded interviews with labor union leaders, an oral history project that was contracted by the New York City Central Labor Council in 1987. The second part is a mix of oral histories and recorded NYC CLC meetings that occured between 1999 and 2005. Discussions cover labor issues in New York City dating from the origins of the organization in the 1920s to 2006.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Access to audiovisual materials in this collection is available through digitized access copies. Researchers may view an item's original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that have already been digitized are noted in the collection's finding aid and can be requested in our reading room.
Labor unions -- New York (N.Y.); Labor leaders -- New York (N.Y.); Labor unions and communism -- New York (State) -- New York.
- Harry Avrutin (Part 1), Jul 29 & Aug 7, 1987; cuid1054A
  Scope and Contents
  Union organization and merger, transport strike, leaflet campaign
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  Original format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 63 min.
  - Access Copy (Box 1, Cd cuid1054A_1-2)
  - Interview Summary -- Parts 1-3 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Original Recording (Box 2, Cassette 1A)
- Harry Avrutin (Part 2), Jul 29 & Aug 7, 1987; cuid1054B
  - Access Copy (Box 1, Cd cuid1054B_1-2)
  - Original Recording (Box 2, Cassette 1B)
- Harry Avrutin (Part 3), Jul 29 & Aug 7, 1987; cuid1054C
  - Access Copy (Box 1, Cd cuid1054C_1-2)
  - Original Recording (Box 2, Cassette 1C)
- Peter Brennan; Exec. board rep,'30s-'70s union history, organizing teachers, cab drivers, etc. -- Parts 1-2, Sep 3, 1987; cuid266A
  General
  Transcript Available
  Original Format: 1/8" audiocassette
  - Access Copy -- Part 1 (Box 1, Cd cuid266A_1-2)
  - Access Copy -- Part 2 (Box 1, Cd cuid266B_1-2)
  - Original Recording -- Part 1 (Box 2, Cassette 2A)
  - Original Recording -- Part 2 (Box 2, Cassette 2B)
  - Transcript -- Parts 1-2 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Leon Davis; Vice President, Harry van Arsdale's union activity (Part 1), Jul 7, 1987; cuid1055A
  - Access Copy (Box 1, Cd cuid1055A_1-2)
  - Interview Summary -- Parts 1-2 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Original Recording (Box 2, Cassette 3A)
- Leon Davis; Vice President, Harry van Arsdale's union activity (Part 2), Jul 7, 1987; cuid1055B
  Original format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 24 min., Preservation note: Side 2 is blank
  - Access Copy (Box 1, Cd cuid1055B_1)
  - Original Recording (Box 2, Cassette 3B)
- Theodore Kheel; Deputy director, profile of 1949, 1962 newspaper strike, van Arsdale (Part 1), Jul 9 & Jul 23, 1987; cuid1056A
  - Access Copy (Box 1, Cd cuid1056A_1-2)
  - Interview Summary -- Parts 1-4 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Original Recording (Box 2, Cassette 4A)
- Theodore Kheel; Deputy director, profile of 1949, 1962 newspaper strike, van Arsdale (Part 2), Jul 9 & Jul 23, 1987; cuid1056B
  Original format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 62 min.
  - Access Copy (Box 1, Cd cuid1056B_1-2)
  - Original Recording (Box 2, Cassette 4B)
- Theodore Kheel; Deputy director, profile of 1949, 1962 newspaper strike, van Arsdale (Part 3), Jul 9 & Jul 23, 1987; cuid1056C
  - Access Copy (Box 1, Cd cuid1056C_1-2)
  - Original Recording (Box 2, Cassette 4C)
- Theodore Kheel; Deputy director, profile of 1949, 1962 newspaper strike, van Arsdale (Part 4), Jul 9 & Jul 23, 1987; cuid1056D
  Original format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 15 min., Preservation note: Side 2 is blank
  - Access Copy (Box 1, Cd cuid1056D_1)
  - Original Recording (Box 2, Cassette 4D)
- Michael Mann; Regional director, organizing taxi drivers, typographers (Part 1), Sep 19, 1987; cuid1057A
  - Access Copy (Box 1, Cd cuid1057A_1-2)
  - Interview Summary -- Parts 1-2 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Original Recording (Box 2, Cassette 5A)
- Michael Mann; Regional director, organizing taxi drivers, typographers (Part 2), Sep 19, 1987; cuid1057B
  Original format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 11 min., Preservation note: Side 2 is blank
  - Access Copy (Box 1, Cd cuid1057B_1)
  - Original Recording (Box 2, Cassette 5B)
- William Michelson; Department Store Workers; organizing 1930's; Exec. board member, union merger, van Arsdale leadership -- Parts 1-2, Aug 13, 1987; cuid1629
  - Access Copy -- Parts 1-2 (Box 1, Cd cuid1629_6A-B)
  - Interview Summary -- Parts 1-2 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Original Recording -- Part 1 (Box 2, Cassette 6A)
  - Original Recording -- Part 2 (Box 2, Cassette 6B)
- Peter Ottley; Organizing NY hospitals, cuid1058
  Original format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 49 min.
  - Access Copy (Box 1, Cd cuid1058_1-2)
  - Interview Summary (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Original Recording (Box 2, Cassette 7)
- Bertram Powers; On the 1962, 1974 newspaper strikes, van Arsdale, picket line violence (Part 1), Jun 24 & Jul 6, 1987; cuid1059A
  Original format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 64 min.
  - Access Copy (Box 1, Cd cuid1059A_1-2)
  - Interview Summary -- Parts 1-2 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Original Recording (Box 2, Cassette 8A)
- Bertram Powers; On the 1962, 1974 newspaper strikes, van Arsdale, picket line violence (Part 2), Jun 24 & Jul 6, 1987; cuid1059B
  Original format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 48 min.
  - Access Copy (Box 1, Cd cuid1059B_1-2)
  - Original Recording (Box 2, Cassette 8B)
- Irving Stern; Organizing Amalgamated Meatcutters, van Arsdale and Farm Workers, edu., Jul 30 & Aug 6, 1987; cuid1060A
  - Access Copy (Box 1, Cd cuid1060A_1-2)
  - Interview Summary -- Parts 1-2 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Original Recording (Box 2, Cassette 9A)
- Irving Stern; Organizing Amalgamated Meatcutters, van Arsdale and Farm Workers, edu. (Part 2), Jul 30 & Aug 6, 1987; cuid1060B
  Original format: 1/8" audiocasette, Duration: 61 min.
  - Access Copy (Box 1, Cd 1060B_1-2)
  - Original Recording (Box 2, Cassette 9B)
- Robert Wagner; Assemblyman, politics of labor '50s-'60s, American Labor Party, 1962 newspaper strike (Part 1), Aug 5-11, 1987; cuid1061A
  - Access Copy (Box 1, Cd cuid1061A_1-2)
  - Interview Summary -- Parts 1-3 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Original Recording (Box 2, Cassette 10A)
- Robert Wagner Assemblyman, politics of labor '50s-'60s, American Labor Party, 1962 newspaper strike (Part 2), Aug 5-11, 1987; cuid1061B
  - Access Copy (Box 1, Cd cuid1061B_1-2)
  - Original Recording (Box 2, Cassette 10B)
- Robert Wagner; Assemblyman, politics of labor '50s-'60s, American Labor Party, 1962 newspaper strike (Part 3), Aug 5-11, 1987; cuid1061C
  Original format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 29 min., Preservation note: Side 2 is blank
  - Access Copy (Box 1, Cd cuid1061C_1)
  - Original Recording (Box 2, Cassette 10C)
- Gerald Waters; Businesss rep., Central Labor Council, Jul 28, 1987; cuid1062
  Original format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 63 min., Preservation note: Sporadic electronic interference on the source tape
  - Access Copy (Box 1, Cd cuid1062_1-2)
  - Interview Summary (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Original Recording (Box 2, Cassette 11)
- Brian McLaughlin, cuid1065
  Original format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 60 min., Preservation note: Content in left channel only, but remixed into both channels. Side 2 is blank.
  - Access Copy (Box 1, Cd cuid1065_1)
  - Original Recording (Box 2, Cassette 013)
- Sam Greenfield Interview: Brian McLaughlin AFL/CIO, cuid1066
  Original format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 64 min., Preservation Note: Side 2 is blank.
  - Access Copy (Box 1, Cd cuid1066_1)
  - Original Recording (Box 2, Cassette 014)
- Julius Margolin & George Mann, cuid1067
  Original format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 57 min.
  - Access Copy (Box 1, Cd cuid1067_1-2)
  - Original Recording (Box 2, Cassette 015)
- Bertram Powers -- Transcript, July 18, 1996; TW_OH_007_ER_1
- The Labor Exchange, May 15, 1999; May 29, 1999; cuid1069
  Side A- First Interview at the Labor Exchange Station - KGNU - Boulder, Colorado, May 15th, 1999 / Side B - Second Interview at the Labor Exchange Station - KGNU - Boulder, Colorado - May 29, 1999
  Original format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 76 min.
  - Access Copy (Box 1, Cd cuid1069_1-2)
  - Original Recording (Box 2, Cassette 016)
- New York City Central Labor Council "Rally", April 4, 1999; cuid1068
  Original format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 2 min., Preservation Note: Side 1 is only 2 minutes long, Side 2 is blank.
  - Access Copy (Box 1, Cd cuid1068_1)
  - Original Recording (Box 2, Cassette 016)
- Central Labor Council, September 8, 2000; cuid1070
  Original format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 3 min., Preservation note: Side 1 is only 3 min. long, Side 2 is blank.
  - Access Copy (Box 1, Cd cuid1070_1)
  - Original Recording (Box 2, Cassette 018)
- Julius Margolin & George Mann, June 5, 2000; cuid1071
  - Access Copy (Box 1, Cd cuid1071_1-2)
  - Original Recording (Box 2, Cassette 019)
- Brian McLaughlin & James McGowan, August 28, 2000; August 30, 2000; cuid1072
  Labor Lines, hosted by Vic Fusco: A program about working men and women and the organizations that represent them. / At NYS-AFL-CIO Concention NYC / Honorable James McGowan, NYS Commissioner of Labor / Honarable Brian McLaughlin, NYS Assembly and President NYC Central Labor Council
  Original format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 63 min., Preservation note: Side 2 is blank.
  - Access Copy (Box 1, Cd cuid1072_1)
  - Original Recording (Box 2, Cassette 020)
- OTL, January 8, 2001; cuid1073
  Original format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 56 min., Preservation note: Poor broadcast signal on source tape.
  - Access Copy (Box 1, Cd cuid1073_1-2)
  - Original Recording (Box 2, Cassette 021)
- Margolin, Mann, & Fusco, March 9, 2003; cuid1074
  Labor Lines Interview Radio with George Mann and Julius Marglin With Vic Fusco / Labor Station WGBB L.I. - Labor-Folk-Politician
  Original format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 59 min.
  - Access Copy (Box 1, Cd cuid1074_1-2)
  - Original Recording (Box 2, Cassette 022)
- Julius Margolin & George Mann, June 26, 2005; cuid1075
  Original format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 50 min.
  - Access Copy (Box 1, Cd cuid1075_1-2)
  - Original Recording (Box 4, Vhs 054)
  - Original Recording (Box 2, Cassette 023)
- NYC CLC Executive Board, May 19, 2005; cuid1076
  Original format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 95 min., Preservation note: Recorded @ .9375 ips, time stretched to 1 7/8 ips...Side 2 is blank.
  - Access Copy -- Part 1 (A) (Box 1, Cd cuid1076_1_A)
  - Access Copy -- Part 2 (B) (Box 1, Cd cuid1076_1_B)
  - Original Recording (Box 2, Cassette 024)
- NYC CLC Delegates, May 19, 2005; cuid1077
  Original format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 66 min., Preservation note: Content recorded @ .9375 ips, time stretched to 1 7/8 ips, Side 2 is blank.
  - Access Copy (Box 1, Cd cuid1077_1_A-B)
  - Original Recording (Box 3, Cassette 025)
- NYC CLC Executive Board, June 16, 2005; cuid1078
  Original format: 1/8" audiocasssette, Duration: 108 min., Content recorded @ .9375 ips, time stretched to 1 7/8 ips; Side 2 is blank
  - Access Copy -- Part 1 (A) (Box 1, Cd cuid1078_1_A)
  - Access Copy -- Part 2 (B) (Box 1, Cd cuid1078_1_B)
  - Original Recording (Box 3, Cassette 026)
- NYC CLC Executive Board, December 15, 2005; cuid1079
  Original format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 24 min., Preservation note: Content recorded @ .9375 ips, time stretched to 1 7/8 ips; Side 2 is blank
  - Access Copy (Box 1, Cd cuid1079_1)
  - Original Recording (Box 3, Cassette 027)
- NYC CLC Executive Board, April 20, 2006; cuid1081
  Original format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 91 min., Preservation note: Content recorded @ .9375 ips, time stretched to 1 7/8 ips; Side 2 is blank.
  - Access Copy -- Part 1 (A) (Box 1, Cd cuid1081_1_A)
  - Access Copy -- Part 2 (B) (Box 1, Cd cuid1081_1_B)
  - Original Recording (Box 3, Cassette 029)
- NYC CLC Delegates, May 18, 2006; cuid1082
  Original format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 60 min., Preservation note: Content recorded @ .9375 ips, time stretched to 1 7/8 ips; Side 2 is blank
  - Access Copy (Box 1, Cd cuid1082_1_A-B)
  - Original Recording (Box 3, Cassette 030)
- NYC CLC Executive Board, January 20, 2005; cuid1085
  Original format: Mini-cassette, Duration 61 min.
  - Access Copy (Box 1, Cd cuid1085_1-2)
  - Original Recording (Box 3, Compact cassette 033)
- NYC CLC Delegates, February 3, 2005; cuid1086
  Original format: Mini-cassette, Duration: 21 min., Preservation note: Side 2 is blank.
  - Access Copy (Box 1, Cd cuid1086_1)
  - Original Recording (Box 3, Compact cassette 034)
- NYC CLC Executive Board, February 7, 2005; cuid1087
  Original format: Mini-cassette, Duration 47 min., Preservation note: Side 2 is blank.
  - Access Copy (Box 1, Cd cuid_1087_1)
  - Original Recording (Box 3, Compact cassette 035)
- NYC CLC Executive Board, March 17, 2005; cuid1088
  Original format: Mini-cassette, Duration: 87 min., Preservation note: Side 2 is blank.
  - Access Copy -- Part 1 (Box 1, Cd cuid1088_1_A)
  - Access Copy -- Part 2 (Box 1, Cd cuid1088_1_B)
  - Original Recording (Box 3, Compact cassette 036)
- NYC CLC Delegates, March 17, 2005; cuid1089
  Original format: Mini-cassette, Duration: 49 min., Preservation note: Side 2 is blank.
  - Access Copy (Box 1, Cd cuid1089_1)
  - Original Recording (Box 3, Compact cassette 037)
- NYC CLC Executive Board, April 21, 2005; cuid1090
  Original format: Mini-cassette, Duration: 51 min., Preservation note: Side 2 is blank.
  - Access Copy (Box 1, Cd cuid1090_1)
  - Original Recording (Box 3, Compact cassette 038)
- NYC CLC Executive Board, February 16, 2006; cuid1080
  Original format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 68 min., Preservation note: Content recorded @ .9375 ips, time stretched to 1 7/8 ips; Side 2 is blank
  - Access Copy (Box 1, Cd cuid1080_1_A-B)
  - Original Recording (Box 3, Cassette 028)
- NYC CLC Executive Board, May 18, 2006; cuid1083
  Original format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 61 min., Preservation note: Content recorded @ .9375 ips, time stretched to 1 7/8 ips; Side 2 is blank.
  - Access Copy (Box 1, Cd cuid1083_1_A-B)
  - Original Recording (Box 3, Cassette 031)
- NYC CLC Executive Board, June 15, 2006; cuid1084
  Original format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 71 min., Preservation note: Content recorded @ .9375 ips, time stretched to 1 7/8 ips; Side 2 is blank.
  - Access Copy (Box 1, Cd cuid1084_1_A-B)
  - Original Recording (Box 3, Cassette 032)
- Angelica/Angelique -- Partial Transcript, undated; TW_OH_007_ER_2
- Unidentified Recordings
  - Original Recording -- 039 (Box 3, Cassette 039)
  - Original Recording -- 040 (Box 3, Cassette 040)
  - Original Recording -- 041 (Box 3, Cassette 041)
  - Original Recording -- 042 (Box 3, Cassette 042)
  - Original Recording -- 043 (Box 3, Cassette 043)
  - Original Recording -- 044 (Box 3, Cassette 044)
  - Original Recording -- 045 (Box 3, Cassette 045)
  - Original Recording -- 046 (Box 3, Cassette 046)
  - Original Recording -- 047 (Box 3, Cassette 047)
  - Original Recording -- 048 (Box 3, Cassette 048)
  - Original Recording -- 049 (Box 3, Cassette 049)
  - Original Recording -- 050 (Box 3, Cassette 050)
  - Original Recording -- 051 (Box 3, Cassette 051)
  - Original Recording -- 052 (Box 3, Cassette 052)
  - Original Recording -- 053 (Box 3, Cassette 053)